[Music]
hi and welcome to this session you
probably know us but uh my name is Peter
boring and with me I have my name is
Mike B Cardona and we're going to talk
to you about uh customization in
business Central now business Central
has powerful customization tooling that
is built into the web client and really
allows our customers to adapt quickly uh
to change to their uh to their needs um
it's this highly interactive and very
immersive experience that is baked into
the client and uh really because it's in
your browser it's alongside the data
that you have loaded up you get this
instant sense of how your changes uh
look and feel and behave alongside your
data yeah and ultimately it's all about
empowering people to quickly optimize
their experience for how they work uh or
how their business operate and that's
why we are super excited today to
present this new capability uh this
addition to our UI customization tooling
which is the ability to add existing
table fields to your pages to optimize
your pages and we really think that this
is going to help our customers uh get to
Value faster and at lower cost which
means the overall total cost of
ownership of business Central goes down
yes and not only that but it also helps
scaling our partners right Consultants
are empowered to do more and with this
we also free up the scar developer
resources exactly and we should also
mention Peter that isn't this one of the
most highly voted Community ideas of all
time yes I think it's amongst the top
two in fact six 600 votes or something
like that something like that yes um we
should also mention that um if we look
to Modern Workforce Trends uh the trend
is towards workers being more willing
more competent as well to take on these
kind of customizations themselves they
feel that they can take on this kind of
work and they want to take on this work
as well yes and it's true to our spirit
adapt quickly so let's get on with it
let's do that yes so let's look at the
agenda for this session so um we'll
start up with talking about some of the
user experience enhancements uh that we
have introduced that that helps you when
you're doing C izations or Ro
customizations or just working in the
extension designer we'll also talk about
how you can make Fields read only in the
experience and then uh last but not
least we're going to talk about the
ability to add existing table fields to
a page allowing consultants and inducers
a quick no code way of customizing
existing pages so Mike can you talk a
little bit about the user experiences
absolutely let's start right there in
fact this is quite important to
understand how to add table Fields uh
it's important to understand uh how the
user experience has changed in update 23
U keep in mind that whether it's
personalization whether it's role
customization or using the extension
designer uh this is pretty much the same
experience that you have now now um each
of these uh give you more transparency
into the fields that you want to add to
the page um but also you know answer
questions like what is this field about
uh where does it come from you'll be
able to answer all of those questions
thanks to this revised user experience
we've also made it a lot more efficient
to work with large tables which have a
lot of fields in fact we have some
tables that have more than 100 Fields
more than 200 Fields as well so we're
also supporting scale here for large
tables where you need to find the right
field at the right point in time let's
dive into a
demo let's start right here on the
vendor list I'm going to start by
personalizing just to illustrate the
experience let's go to
personalize now I'm going to bring up
the ad field
Pane and that slides in from the right
hand side there we go and notice first
of all how the fields listed in the pane
here are uh you know they show very
little information they're really just
meant to give you a very quick sense of
of of what the field is so we've got a
field caption shown over there we've got
the field data type as well and the new
icon which shows if this is a field that
is visible on the page or not visible
currently on the page but sometimes we
need more context to decide if this is
the right field for me so as I hover
over these fields you'll notice that we
have a new tool tip that appears that
gives you some of that context let's
hover over coupled with data verse uh
here you can see in the tool tip we have
some useful information we have the
caption again but also because the table
field and the Page Field May sometimes
have a slightly different uh name we're
also showing the alternate name here as
well also known as coupled to CRM uh
we've got the tool tip in there the
field tool tip as well from the page
that explains what this is all about now
I understand that this field uh couples
the vendor record with an account in
data verse uh we also share additional
information through that tool tip we've
got um things like a you know is this
specified on the page object but also
where did it come from this came from
the base application it's defined in the
base application by Microsoft Microsoft
is the publisher of this particular
field now you'll notice also up here
recommended Fields what does this term
mean well we're introducing this term to
imply these are the fields that have
been added by the developer onto the
page and developers often choose to show
the fields that all of their users need
but they'll choose to hide some of the
fields that only some of their users
tend to need so that's what we mean by
recommended fields in this place so here
because I am personalizing I have access
to these recommended Fields um and to
explain even further what recommended
Fields actually means you can take a
look at the advanced filters here so
recommended Fields is kind of a way of
filtering the entire list of vendor uh
uh fields on the vendor table right look
at what's in here in these Advanced
filters this kind of explains what you
see in that list of fields we see fields
that are bound to a table in other words
they originate from the vendor table in
this case we have fields that are page
controls uh which means they're actually
not bound to a table field they're
actually just bound to a variable uh you
can uh also toggle sort of show me only
or include only fields from the base
objects or from extensions but also
visibility and these are fully
adjustable so if recommended Fields is a
good starting point for you you'd use
that but if you want more control just
to find the fields you're looking for
you'd use this filtering ability so
let's do one little exercise here I'm
going to check Fields already shown on
the page and now notice how the uh the
list here has been updated in fact
you'll see that the icons have changed
right some fields are hidden on the page
some fields are visible on the page as
implied by that icon so we're helping
you at a glance get a sense of what is
this field but ultimately all the fields
here are presented in a very similar way
just to reduce the amount of complexity
as you start using this feature and
finding your
Fields let me uncheck that
again okay so let's go through a little
exercise now that we've understand how
the new filter control works it presents
recommended fields and I can adjust
those filters as well let's try and add
um the country region field onto the
page so here it is country region code
again the tool tip will tell me how this
works if I click on Country region code
in the pane business Central will scroll
that field into view on the page
canvas uh it will show it in this way
which implies it's not actually visible
yet on the page I still have one more
task to do to to make sure I want it to
become visible for my users or for
myself in this case because I'm
personalizing but here you you can see
it is a recommended field that is shown
also in the recommended position the
recommended location on the page why
because again a developer thoughtfully
put it into that place and now we're
helping users you know make sure that
the field they'd like to uh make visible
on the page is in the best possible
location so from here I can now hover
over the field itself and choose to show
that field that is the first way in
which I can bring Fields onto my page
when I'm personalizing
um now again keep in mind this is a
field recommended by the developer it's
already sort of coded into the page I'm
simply making it visible I can reverse
that decision as well by hiding it again
off the page and notice how each time
the pain on the right will adjust will
adapt uh we're trying to create an
experience here which feels very
physical you know as the field uh on the
right and the pain uh as that is
transferred onto the page disappears
from the pain itself and I want to show
you a alternate way of bringing Fields
onto the page let's do the same exercise
this time I'm going to drag and drop the
field I'm going to take country region
code again going to drag it with my
mouse and because I'm dragging it uh
notice first of all how I have a mouse
pointer hint uh that tells me that I'm
about to move it to a particular
location it's not the one that the
developer originally intended but that's
okay I've got the flexibility to choose
precisely where I want it now i' like
country region code to show up uh let's
put this after the context field now
there we go and as I drop again same
story it appears in place the data loads
up um so again I'm seen the data live as
I make changes uh and that field has
disappeared from the pane on the right
so that's how you can filter to reduce
the set of fields but you can also
search for your field and the two work
great together so here alongside my
filtering I'm also going to say find me
the country or region code it's not
going to find that field because I've
got it on the page let's hide it from
here again
there we go so I've got search working
with my filters I found the country
region code field uh and as I navigate
to a different page for example here I'm
navigating to the vendor card notice how
business Central preserves my Search
terms and my filters uh so that I can
continue working on this page as well
because I'm probably performing similar
customizations in this case all right
now in this case uh a lot of what I
showed you on the list page applies here
as well I'm going to drag the region
code let's place it here under zip code
very well um so it's the same kind of
Concepts right the same way of
interacting with things once it's here I
can move it to a different location I've
also got the usual menu of capabilities
to work with that field and customize it
further but there's a new one there's a
new menu item here which is about
editing or editability now in this case
um I'm showing the country region code
field on the page and I can also make it
read only I can lock editting using this
menu item now it's readon which means
I'm creating visual focus on the
editable fields it's one of those things
that you know I don't want to enter
values into so like this I can easily
skip over it it's a great way to
optimize your pages further for
readability and also prevent any data
editing accidents where you might
accidentally set that to something
different um now I can also revert my
change so I'm going to say unlock
editing and now we're back to normal so
now this field can be edited again so
it's very simple any editable field you
can lock it and then you can revert your
change by unlocking it I want to be
really clear about what we mean by
making things editable here or unlocking
unlocking Fields is something you would
do to a field you have already locked
which means if the developer has already
defined on this page for example the
balance field here this field is never
meant to be editable you'll notice that
I actually don't have the ability to
unlock and make this editable safety
first we want to make sure we preserve
the Integrity of our customers data and
even though these are very powerful
tools we want to make sure that it don't
get into a situation where they can edit
data they should never be editing
because that may have Downstream
implications uh in business
Central so that was a quick demo of the
user experience uh but also the ability
to lock and unlock fields for
editability very good so all of that is
available whether you're personalizing
your workspace for yourself whether
you're making uh rooll tailored
adjustments to business Central for all
users in a role or if you're designing
extensions um now we should really
switch to what is the star of the show
let's talk about adding existing table
fields to optimize your pages this is
really the very first time in history
that we're uh going beyond the concept
of recommended Fields uh and we're
really empowering customers to pick from
any fields from that Source table that
powers the page including extensions and
bring that in into the page so they can
consume it they can read it they can
view it we are launching this capability
in preview with update 23 and let me
give you a quick demo of
that now adding existing table Fields is
something you can only do in roll
customization so the first thing I will
do is will I go to my list of profiles
also known as
roles let's go to that list I'm going to
pick one of these roles let pick the
bookkeeper role and just say customize
Pages this is going to open up a new tab
with business Central is going to zoom
into the bookkeeper profile and now I
can begin customizing which means that
any user assigned this profile will be
able to see these changes let's go to
posted documents I'll go to posted sales
invoices I'll bring up the very same
pain now this is the same add a field
pain that you saw earlier for
personalization this time for RO
customization notice one very
significant change which is the filter
now says all Fields It also says in
preview as I mentioned earlier uh but
ultimately now because I'm customizing
roles and I've got permission to
actually uh pick from all fields that
becomes a new default view inside the
pane which means now I don't only have
recommended Fields here I've got all the
fields including those from The Source
table look at the size of that scroll
bar there are so many more things I can
pick from from the to adjust my posted
sales invoices in this case
now you also notice if you go to the
advanced filters here that one new
filter has also lit up which is table
Fields not on the page object that's
exactly what these are that we've
included here this is exactly what we're
unlocking and empowering our customers
to bring onto their Pages as a very
quick example let's go to one of these
posted sales
invoices and here I'd like to find the
remaining
amount now this is a well let's use the
tool tip this is defined on the table
it's only on the table no developer has
added it to this page but I really need
to see the remaining amount on this
posted invoice so what I'm going to do
is same thing I can either click to show
it in place here business Central will
add it to the end of the fast tab or the
end of the list just to give you a
starting point where you can choose to
sort of display that remaining amount
right or I could just drag it into the
exact location where I'd like it to show
let's have it show somewhere here there
it is remaining amount now because this
came from a table and this is the first
time it's been added to the page you can
only get this to a readon state every
table field you add will be
readon uh in most cases it'll also load
up the data for that field instantly
there'll be a few cases where it does
not so you need to refresh or just
simply rigate back to the page and to
load up that data so here you have the
remaining amount field for the very
first time on the posted sales invoice
with that value that I can see alongside
all of my other fields now it's the same
concept again whether it's on a c card
page a list page or any other page type
you'd interact with your fields and drop
them onto your page in exactly the same
way now I'm done with my changes so I
hit done and at this point um all users
again that are assigned this profile are
able to start seeing the remaining
amount field uh on this page um now I I
did this in a sandbox right and one
benefit of that is because I'm in a
sandbox I can uh test my changes I can
get others invite others to test the
changes with me as well and when I'm
really comfortable with the changes I've
made I can always export my role
customizations and then import them into
production at the right point in time
and that's also great from a safety
perspective you know want to again
practice safety first uh make sure that
the changes you're making here are ideal
they have no Downstream consequences um
and are ready to consume in production
so to tell us more about creating a safe
experience Peter over to you thank you
Mike I mean this is an awesome uh
feature right but as as Mike alluded to
uh multiple times in the demo we really
wanted to make sure that that this is
safe for the primary audience of this
feature so consultants and
administrators but also for for end
users right and so uh
first H as Mike mentioned this is for
role customization only right we focus
on the users who naturally already have
some degree of technical understanding
it also reduces the risk of uh end users
you know going about and creating
disruption basically by creating pockets
of of functionality or variability on
the pages and as we saw uh it's a way of
working in a sandbox and then importing
in a production when ready to reduce
risk you know you export this to a to
inspect and uh in the flow here you can
add these things as Ro customization if
it doesn't fit the end specific end user
they can you know always go and hide
that as a personalization
afterwards then as we saw the added
fields are read only that's a natural
fit for for list places but it also
removes the risk of unintentional
editing in in card
Pages then as mentioned we um we
introduced a permission also to make
sure uh that um you do not have the
option to add these fields unless you
have the permission we'll talk about
that in a in a moment and also uh
another thing we'll talk more about is
that we want to give Partners partner
developers the ability to opt out Fields
so that they cannot be added or are not
shown in the fields uh pain maybe they
are you know sensitive or internal or
something like that don't really make
sense for the End customer to
have if we have a look at the permission
what we done there is that we added a
new uh add table field to page uh
permission uh in the uh d 365 profile
management permission set H so that fits
naturally with the other permission for
profile management and as I said for
developers we created a new property on
table field which is called allowing
customizations which you can set to
never or always right and if you set it
to never uh we will actually you know
not include that field and we can see
the impact of that we have some example
code here where in the first version I
do not nothing that basically means that
it will be available so in the
experience that Mike shown before that
table field can be selected and it can
be added in the page right but then
later maybe in my uh versions for the
app I have decided that I would not want
to allow this so I add the allow and
customization never in code and that
then means that it will no longer be on
the page I mean we will take it away
even though it was added before it's
going to you know apply instantly and
it's also not going to be in the list of
fields to add of course you can you know
um decide at some point that you want to
show this again so again in code you set
this to always and that means that then
the table field is automatically added
back in the UI if it was added before
right and it will also be available
again in the fields
list so there's a couple of things uh to
be aware of um you can add flow fields
and flow Fields include calculations and
that could be large calculations right
so if you add a lot of flow fields to
one single page that could have a
performance impact and it's just
something to be you know be aware of or
have in mind then another thing here is
that when you have a you know when you
when you add a table field to a page
it's of course backed by that table
field and so that table field could be
removed at some point in the future you
know maybe it's part of a pretending
extension it it gets removed and that's
really the same as today you know that
can happen today uh the result is that
the field will not show up in the page
we'll just suppress that and you can use
the page customizations troubleshooting
pain uh sorry page to see uh any issues
that you might have uh with
customizations and you know Rectify
those also Mike talked about that we
will put in know when you add that field
to the page P you will put in data uh we
are respecting if you use the extended
data type mask for uh for example for um
passwords right so the data for those
will not be shown in the PTI Spector and
the field the value will be masked in
the field when you added it to the page
or a
list now this functionality does not
replace extensions because you can still
do U many you know scenarios um or more
complicated scenarios in extensions that
you cannot do with this feature and
that's specifically when you want to
have more advanced field Behavior so for
example you could have properties on
both table and Pages uh that that that
do something right like validation
triggers and in this scenario that we
have where we add a field you only get
the functionality that is on the table
field right because there is no existing
Page Field we create a page field for
that table field so we can only look at
that table field so if you you know it's
it's not
good practice but if you only have say
validation on the page other pages that
has that field but nothing on the table
you will not get that kind of validation
when you add the the field uh to a given
page
yourself um then there are certain
properties that are today only available
on Page Field and again since this is a
scenario where we create a new page
field um you're not getting this so that
could be tool tips or assist edit drop-
down functionality Etc because they are
usually done in code right and you will
have to revert to extensions to to
handle that there could be scenarios
where the field needs to participate in
an interaction with other fields maybe
you have you know color highlighting
with the row style expression for
example for traffic colors H maybe you
have you know fields that multiple
fields that contribute to totals or or
Wizards with some control over field
logic Etc fields that needs to go
together that's business logic as as
well and needs to be created in
extensions we talked about that Fields
will be non-editable so if you need the
field to be editable you need to add it
through an extension today and then last
but not least um we create these as
roles and roles are not organizational
wide right so if you want something
which is really for every single user
then currently you need to create it it
through an extension I mean the
alternative is you can of course go in
and modify these for all the roles that
get exposed to that page that's that's
the mitigation on this now there is you
know for some of this if we just go back
you might wonder you know how do I know
whether there's difference between
existing uh you know having that feel in
existing Pages do those pages add some
specific functionality that I will miss
if I just add that field directly from a
table maybe you know if that function is
not on the table hey well there's
actually in this release a new very
powerful tool that can help you with
that and that is in the page inspection
uh tab there's a new Option uh called
explore page in Visual Studio code and
also on the table Fields there's an
option for exploring in Visual Studio
code and what um those opt those links
do is that they actually provision
visual studio for you with everything
with all the you know extensions that
are part of this page so if you go to
the extensions tab you will see all of
the extensions that contribute to this
page we'll create a project with all of
those allowing you to inspect the source
there with one click you don't have to
you know Consultants can do this if they
can read code and have Visual Studio
code installed we have one example here
uh if you go on the field and you
invoked explore Studio code it will
directly get you to the source code for
the field on the table if you use the
page link on top you will get to the
source for the page so that's a way for
you to compare across Pages what was
there any specific functionality
implemented on these pages that I would
lose if I just added to a new page so uh
all of this we go through with demo and
in detail in the and we actually renamed
that session so it's not called what's
new inh but what's new in developer
tools I'm sorry about that but the
session code is the same
uh so go and view that and if you're a
consultant viewing this session you know
just jump to that section in the in this
developer session and don't be afraid of
that it's it's really useful for
Consultants um as well or mainly so um
one last thing here H because we built
this uh for uh you know role
customization in the client we also get
the same backing functionality in a page
customization Al uh implementation right
so as a developer you can now also add
page fields and groups in this way um
but again you know for most scenarios
the page extension would be recommended
because that's the that's the way that
you can add functionality and code right
but if you have very simple scenarios as
developer if you just want to have this
out of the box you can do it in page
customizations so to look back at this
session H you know we reached the end uh
what did we show well we showed some
really exciting features that we hope
you like around improving the user
experience when you're doing
personalization role customization and
working in the extension designer we
also showed you how you can make Fields
read only and uh not least we showed you
the ability to add existing table fields
to a page to allow both consultants and
administrators and end users you know a
quick no code way of customizing
existing
pages and this is such a powerful
combination of features uh that we have
today uh especially for Consultants
right and we've also given control uh to
developers to administrators to make
sure this is a safe experience so
fantastic we're so pleased with how it
turned out and we hope you love this
feature too so if you can spare just a
few more minutes of your time we
recommend these sessions here where we
Deep dive into other web client
productivity features as well uh also
customization doesn't stop at pushing
fields around your page uh you can also
uh get to custom Data Insights using uh
analysis views and we go into a lot of
detail in this session but also finally
U as Peter mentioned if you're more
technically inclined we have the whole
what's new in developer tool session as
well for that
one there's plenty more resources uh if
you're looking to get started with
business Central uh follow the buzz on
social media or just engage with a
project engineering team such as
ourselves and don't forget adding an
existing field from the table to the
page originated as a community idea so
if you've got more great ideas that can
enhance uh our customers productivity um
submit your ideas at aka.
msbc
ideas on behalf of the business Central
team I really want to thank you for
tuning in and see you on the next
session thank
you